Now that we've talked a little bit about
how you can access things from an array
and how you can update them, one of the
things we need to do is we need to talk
about how to add things to the end and
remove them and add things to the front
and remove them. So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to clear out this section.
So I've just got my first names and it's
to Bruce, Tim, and Natasha. So if we
want to add to this array then and we
want to add on to the end then we access
the array and we say first names dot and
because it's an array there's a whole
bunch of things you can do with it. So
you can concatenate, you can copy
within, there's an every function,
there's a for each function. Like
there's a ton of things that you can do
with this. And just to show you that
this is not unique to arrays, we'll say
let my name equal to. If I said my name
dot, you can see that there's a whole
bunch of things that you can do with a
string. So some of the things that you
one of the things that you can do
um with an array is you can add
something to the end. So we could say
let wonderoman
name equal Diana and we could add her
name into the first names list or sorry
first names Ray. Um we'll say first
names dot and the way you add something
is you use the push function. when we
put a parenthesy, it says it needs some
items that you want to add into this
first names um list. So, let's push in
Wonder Woman's name. Once we've done
that, we're going to console.log
first names.
So, we'll save this.
We'll come over to our code. And now you
can see that the array says Toa, Bruce,
Tim, Natasha, and Diana. And it put
Diana directly on at the end of the
array.
Well, let's say you want to remove
something from the array, and you want
to remove something off of the end of
the array.
So,
let's say we want to take Diana off. If
we want to do that, then we can say
first names. Pop.
And if we save that and we come over and
we reload our page. Oh, I forgot to
print it again. We'll add console
console.log
first names. And if we save that and we
come over here, we first get the array
that has Diana added to the end and then
then we get an array that has her
removed from the end.
Well, sometimes you don't want to add to
the end. You want to add to the front.
So, let's do that. So, let's go to our
first names list and then we'll say
unshift. Unshift means take all the
items, shift them over to the right, and
insert something in front. So, let's
unshift Wonder Woman's name.
And then let's console.log that again.
So, if we come back over here, we see
Toa, Bruce, Tim, Natasha, Diana. She was
added to the end. Then we see Toa,
Bruce, Tim, Natasha. She was removed
from the end. Then we see Diana, Toa,
Bruce, Tim, Natasha. And we've stuck
Diana in at the front.
Well, sometimes you also want to get rid
of something from the front. Um, and if
you want to do that, then you say first
names do uh shift.
Shift means take out the first item and
shift everything over to the left.
So if we save that and we come here to
our code. Oh, it would help if I
console.log bit.
So we save that and we come over here.
Now we see Bruce, Tim, Nat Tasha, Diana.
We've added her to the end. To Bruce,
Tim, Natasha, we've removed her from the
end. Diana to Bruce, Tim, Natasha, we've
added her to the front. And then we say
to Bruce, Tim, Natasha, we've now
removed Diana from the front. And um in
that way you can manipulate your array.
Now you may be wondering why would we
want to do this? Well, it's just
different forms of processing. So for
example, if you think about when you go
to the store and you get in line to
check out when you're standing in line,
the first person who got in line is the
first person who gets taken out of the
line. So in that case we're the first
thing we added is being removed from the
front and that is what we call a Q. A
stack is if you think of a stack of
plates at a buffet table they put the
plates at the table and the plates
slowly rise up. The last plate they put
on is the first plate they take off. So
in that case they're removing the very
last item off the end of an array. And
sometimes in your coding you'll want to
do either of those. I don't need you to
remember either of those for now. I just
need you to remember that you can remove
you can add and remove items from the
front and you can add and remove items
from sorry you can add and remove items
from the front and you can add and
remove items from the end. And as long
as you know how to do that you know a
lot about how to manipulate an array.
And that concludes this video. Thanks
for watching.